Marcus E. Lower | Curriculum Vitae

PhD candidate studying pulsars and how we can better understand them through the application Bayesian inference techniques. Research interests include pulsar timing, tests of general relativity, neutron star magnetospheres and astrophysical inference of gravitational-wave sources.

Personal information

Present position: Astrophysics PhD Candidate (expected completion by Dec 2021).

Centre for Astrophysics and Supercomputing, Swinburne University of Technology, PO Box 218, Hawthorn,

VIC 3122, Australia.

Citizenship: Australia, Canada.

Personal webpage: https://astronomy.swin.edu.au/~mlower/

Research experience

Swinburne University of Technology

Melbourne, Australia

Ph.D. candidate, Centre for Astrophysics and Supercomputing

2018-present

- o Support: ARC Laureate Fellow PhD scholarship.
- o Supervisors: Matthew Bailes and Ryan M. Shannon.
- o Thesis: Application of astrophysical inference to next generation pulsar data sets.

Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO)

Sydney, Australia

Ph.D. candidate, Astronomy and Space Science Division

2019-present

- o Support: CSIRO Astronomy and Space Science Studentship.
- o Supervisor: Simon Johnston.

Swinburne University of Technology

Melbourne, Australia

Research Intern, Centre for Astrophysics and Supercomputing

2018

- Responsibilities: Vetting of 600 pulsars for the UTMOST timing program. Developed diagnostic tools for tracking telescope observation efficiency. Follow up parameter estimation of glitches.
- o Supervisors: Matthew Bailes, Chris Flynn, Ryan M. Shannon and Adam Deller.

Education

Monash University

Melbourne, Australia

Bachelor of Science with Honours (first class) in Astrophysics

2017

- o Supervisors: Eric Thrane, Paul D. Lasky and Rory J. E. Smith. Thesis resulted in a publication.
- o *Thesis*: Detecting eccentricity in the orbits of merging binary black holes.

Monash University

Melbourne, Australia

Bachelor of Science in Applied Mathematics and Astrophysics

2014-2016

- o Thesis advisors: Eric Thrane and Letizia Sammut.
- o Undergraduate thesis: Can GW150914 reveal anything about dark matter?

Grants, scholarships and awards

Total awarded: \$89,400

CSIRO Astronomy and Space Science Studentship, CSRIO, \$5k

2019-2021

Faculty of Science Engineering & Technology travel grant, Swinburne University, \$3k

2018-2021

ARC Laureate Fellow PhD Scholarship, Swinburne University, \$81k

2018-2021

OzGrav student travel grant, Swinburne University, \$400

2018

o Covered travel costs for the ANITA Summer School and Workshop in Perth, Australia

Observing proposals

Principal-investigator:

Parkes Radio Telescope:

0	PX057:	Target of opportunity observations of Swift J1818.0—1607. Granted 8 hrs.	2020
0	PX060:	Target of opportunity observation of SGR 1935+2154. Granted 3 hrs.	2020
0	PX067:	Target of opportunity observation of SGR 1830+0645. Granted 1 hrs.	2020

MeerKAT:

0	RB-P11: Timing the invisible B Pulsar of the Double Pulsar system.	2019-2021
0	RB-P12: Probing the magnetosphere of PSR J0737-3039B.	2019-2021

Co-investigator:

Parkes Radio Telescope:

0	P574: Young pulsar timing:	Probing the physics of pulsars and neutron stars. Granted	2020-2021
	100+ hrs.		

P885: Understanding the remarkable behaviour of radio magnetars. Granted 84 hrs.
 P1032: Mass measurements of southern binary pulsar systems. Granted 345 hrs.
 2019-2021
 2019-2021

Teaching

Teaching Assistant:

0	Monash Universit	$_{ m y}$, Earth to cosmos (AS	${\sf SP1010}$; 1st-year undergra	aduate class).	2018
0	Monash Universit	y, Life in the Universe	(ASP1022; 1st-year unde	rgraduate class).	2017

Outreach and service

Outreach activities

0	Guinness World Record for the Most People Stargazing across Multiple Sites (Monash site).	2018
0	Monash University Open Day: science outreach and public engagement activities.	2017
0	Guinness World Record for the Most People Stargazing across Multiple Sites (Monash site).	2015
0	Monash University Open Day: first year physics lab demonstration.	2014

Professional organisation memberships

- o MeerTime Collaboration
- UTMOST Project
- o OzGrav: The ARC Centre for Excellence for Gravitational-Wave Discovery (affiliate)
- Astronomical Society of Australia
- LIGO Scientific Collaboration

Media

 CNET Astronomers trace mysterious fast radio burst to extreme, rare star. 	2020
 Space Australia Ancient Distance Measuring Technique Applied to Magnetar. 	2020
 Space Australia The Dish Helps Study Nearby Magnetar. 	2020
o phys.org Mysterious spinning neutron star detected in the Milky Way proves to be an.	2020
extremely rare discovery.	
• Science Alert Strangely Flaring Dead Star Could Be The 'Missing Link' Between Magnetars	2020
and Pulsars.	
 phys.org Ticking cosmic clocks reveal the evolution of stars over millions of years. 	2020
• Science Alert Astronomers Have Caught This Pulsar Glitching For The Very First Time.	2019
 Space Australia Pulsar Glitches after 30 Years. 	2019

Skills

Programming languages: (proficient) Python, MATLAB, Bash, C shell, (familiar) Mathematica, Fortran90, (basic) C/C++, CUDA.

Software: PSRCHIVE, DSPSR, Tempo2, TempoNest, LIGO-LALSuite, LATEX, GIT, SLURM, HTCondor.

Accumulated observing time: Parkes 150+ hrs.

Publications

Refereed publications: 41; First author: 4; Citations: 3300+ (57 first author); h-index: 23, (ADS)

Listed below are my first author publications in addition to publications where I made a *significant* contribution as a co-author. I am also listed as a co-author on a number of LIGO Scientific Collaboration papers, including the first LIGO-Virgo gravitational-wave transient catalogue (GWTC-1) and the GW190425 detection paper (2nd detected binary neutron-star merger).

First Author (refereed):

- The dynamic magnetosphere of Swift J1818.0—1607
 Lower, S. Johnston, R. M. Shannon, M. Bailes & F. Camilo, MNRAS, in press (arXiv:2011.12463).
- Spectropolarimetric properties of Swift J1818.0—1607: a 1.4s radio magnetar
 M. E. Lower, R. M. Shannon, S. Johnston & M. Bailes, ApJL (2020) 896 L37.
 Covered by press release.
- The UTMOST pulsar timing programme II: Timing noise across the pulsar population
 M. E. Lower, M. Bailes, R. M. Shannon, S. Johnston, C. Flynn, S. Osłowski, V. Gupta, W. Farah, T. Bateman, A. J. Green, R. Hunstead, A. Jameson, F. Jankowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, MNRAS (2020) 494 228.
 Covered by press release.
- 1. Measuring eccentricity in binary black hole inspirals with gravitational waves M. E. Lower, E. Thrane, P. D. Lasky & R. Smith, PRD (2018) 98, 083028.

Co-Author (refereed):

- **12.** Effects of periodicity in observation scheduling on parameter estimation of pulsar glitches L. Dunn, **M. E. Lower** & A. Melatos, MNRAS, submitted.
- 11. The Relativistic Binary Programme on MeerKAT: Science objectives and first results
 M. Kramer, I. H. Stairs, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, et al., inc. M. E. Lower MNRAS, submitted.
- **10.** Gravitational-wave Constraints on the Equatorial Ellipticity of Millisecond Pulsars R. Abbott, T. D. Abbott, S. Abraham et al., inc. **M. E. Lower** ApJL (2020) 902 L21.
- Bayesian inference for compact binary coalescences with Bilby: Validation and application to the first LIGO-Virgo gravitational-wave transient catalogue
 Romero-Shaw, C. Talbot, S. Biscoveanu, et al., inc. M. E. Lower, MNRAS (2020) 499 3295.
- **8.** A magnetar parallax
 - H. Ding, A. T. Deller, **M. E. Lower**, C. Flynn, S. Chatterjee, W. Brisken, N. Hurley-Walker, F. Camilo, J. Sarkissian, V. Gupta, MNRAS (2020) 498 3736.
 - Covered by press release.
- 7. The MeerKAT Telescope as a Pulsar Facility: System verification and early science results from MeerTime M. Bailes, A. Jameson, F. Abbate, et al., inc. M. E. Lower, PASA (2020) 37 e028.
- 6. The Parkes Pulsar Timing Array Project: Second data release M. Kerr, D. J. Reardon, G. Hobbs, R. M. Shannon, R. N. Manchester, S. Dai, C. J. Russell, S.-B. Zhang, W. van Straten, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, R. Spiewak, M. Bailes, N. D. R. Bhat, A. D. Cameron, W. A. Coles, J. Dempsey, X. Deng, B. Goncharov, J. F Kaczmarek, M. J. Keith, P. D. Lasky, M. E. Lower, B. Preisig, J. M. Sarkissian, L. Toomey, H. Wang, J. Wang, L. Zhang, X. Zhu, PASA (2020) 37 e020.
- **5.** The UTMOST Survey for Magnetars, Intermittent pulsars, RRATs and FRBs I: System description and overview
 - V. Venkatraman Krishnan, C. Flynn, W. Farah, A. Jameson, M. Bailes, S. Osłowski, T. Bateman, V. Gupta, W. van Straten, E. F. Keane, E. D. Barr, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. K. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. Hunstead, F. Jankowski, **M. E. Lower**, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, P. A. Rosado & D. Temby, MNRAS (2020) 492 4752.
- Five new real-time detections of Fast Radio Bursts with UTMOST
 W. Farah, C. Flynn, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. K. Day, A. T. Deller, A. J. Green, V. Gupta, R. Hunstead, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, M. Caleb, S.-W. Chang, M. Cruces, J. Roy, V. Morello, C. A. Onken, B. W. Stappers & C. Wolf, MNRAS (2019) 488 2989.
 Covered by press release.

The 2018 X-ray and Radio Outburst of Magnetar XTE J1810–197
 V. Gotthelf, J. P. Halpern, J. A. J. Alford, T. Mihara, H. Negoro, N. Kawai, S. Dai, M. E. Lower, S. Johnston, M. Bailes, S. Osłowski, F. Camilo, H. Miyasaka & K. K. Madsen, ApJL (2019) 874 L25.

- Wideband polarized radio emission from the newly revived radio magnetar XTE J1810-197
 Dai, M. E. Lower, M. Bailes, F. Camilo, J. P. Halpern, S. Johnston, M. Kerr, J. Reynolds, J. Sarkissian & P. Scholz, ApJL (2019) 874 L14.
- Bilby: A user-friendly Bayesian inference library for gravitational-wave astronomy
 G. Ashton, M. Huebner, P. D. Lasky, C. Talbot, K. Ackley, S. Biscoveanu, Q. Chu, A. Divarkala, P. J. Easter,
 B. Goncharov, F. Hernandez Vivanco, J. Harms, M. E. Lower, G. D. Meadors, D. Melchor, E. Payne, M. D. Pitkin, J. Powell, N. Sarin, R. J. E. Smith & E. Thrane, ApJS (2019) 241 27.

Non-peer reviewed publications:

- **16.** *VLBA detection of Swift J1818.0–1607*D. Hao, A. T. Deller, **M. E. Lower** & R. M. Shannon, ATel #14005 (2020).
- 15. Resurgence in the radio flux of the magnetar XTE J1810–197
 M. E. Lower, V. Gupta, C. Flynn, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, A. Mandlik, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #13840 (2020).
- 14. FRB200607 found by UTMOST V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, A. Mandlik, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #13788 (2020).
- No radio counterpart for IGR J18179—1621 detected during a serendipitous VLBA observation H. Ding, A. T. Deller, M. E. Lower & R. M. Shannon, ATel #13737 (2020).
- 12. FRB200508 found at UTMOST
 - V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, A. Mandlik, **M. E. Lower**, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urguhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #13715 (2020).
- 11. Multi-band observations of Swift J1818.0—1607 with Parkes M. E. Lower & R. M. Shannon, ATel #13587 (2020).
- MeerKAT observation of the radio magnetar candidate Swift J1818.0–1607
 M. E. Lower, S. Buchner, S. Johnston, A. Parthasarathy, M. Geyer & M. Bailes on behalf of the MeerTime collaboration, ATel #13562 (2020).
- FRB191223 found at UTMOST
 V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, A. Mandlik, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #13363 (2019).
- Detection of a glitch in PSR J0908–4913 by UTMOST
 M. E. Lower, M. Bailes, R. M. Shannon, S. Johnston, C. Flynn, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. K. Day, A. Deller, W. Farah, A. J. Green, V. Gupta, R. W. Hunstead, A. Jameson, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr & G. Urquhart, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, RNAAS (2019) 3 192.
- 7. FRB191107 found at UTMOST

 V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller,
 A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, A. Mandlik, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #13282 (2019).
- 6. FRB190806 found at UTMOST
 V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, D. C. Price, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #12995 (2019).

- 5. Detection of FRB190322 at the Molonglo Radio Telescope
 V. Gupta, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, W. Farah, T. Bateman, E. D. Barr, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, F. Jankowski, E. F. Keane, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #12610 (2019).
- 4. Detection of FRB181228 at the Molonglo Radio Telescope
 W. Farah, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, V. Gupta, T. Bateman, E. D. Barr, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, F. Jankowski, E. F. Keane, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #12335 (2018).
- Detection of low-frequency radio emission from the magnetar XTE J1810-197
 M. E. Lower, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, W. Farah, C. Flynn, V. Gupta, T. Bateman, E. D. Barr, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, F. Jankowski, E. F. Keane, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart, V. Venkatraman Krishnan & T. Venville, ATel #12288 (2018).
- Two new FRBs discovered by UTMOST
 W. Farah, M. Bailes, A. Jameson, C. Flynn, V. Gupta, T. Bateman, E. D. Barr, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, A. J. Green, R. W. Hunstead, F. Jankowski, E. F. Keane, M. E. Lower, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, A. Sutherland, D. Temby, G. Torr, G. Urquhart & V. Venkatraman Krishnan, ATel #12124 (2018).
- Detection of a glitch in the pulsar J1709–4429
 M. E. Lower, C. Flynn, M. Bailes, E. D. Barr, T. Bateman, S. Bhandari, M. Caleb, D. Campbell-Wilson, C. Day, A. Deller, W. Farah, A. J. Green, V. Gupta, R. W. Hunstead, A. Jameson, F. Jankowski, E. F. Keane, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, S. Osłowski, A. Parthasarathy, K. Plant, D. C. Price, V. Ravi, R. M. Shannon, D. Temby, G. Torr & G. Urguhart, RNAAS (2018) 2 139.

Presentations

1 colloquium (invited), 8 conference talks, 4 department seminars, 2 posters at conferences.

Colloquia

1. Massive scale pulsar timing with the Molonglo Observatory Synthesis Telescope ATNF Colloquium, CSIRO Marsfield, Sydney, Australia, Feb 2020 (Invited).

Conference and workshop presentations

- The radio magnetar XTE J1810—197: A galactic FRB analogue?
 2020 Astronomical Society of Australia Annual Scientific Meeting, held online, July 2020.
- 7. The impact of glitches on the rotational evolution of young pulsars
 PHAROS 2020: The multi-messenger physics and astrophysics of neutron stars, Patras, Greece, Mar 2020
 (postponed due to COVID-19).
- **6.** The UTMOST pulsar timing programme 10th IPTA scientific meeting, Pune, India, Jun 2019.
- **5.** Bayesian pulsar timing and noise analysis with TempoNest 10th IPTA student workshop, NCRA, Pune, India, Jun 2019 (Invited).
- Profile domain timing
 OzGrav Pulsar Timing Inference Workshop, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, May
 2019 (Invited).
- Pulsar inference tools
 OzGrav Pulsar Timing Inference Workshop, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, May 2019 (Invited).
- 2. Measuring rotational instabilities in pulsars with the Molonglo telescope ANITA 2019 workshop, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, Feb 2019.
- Distinguishing eccentricity in binary black hole mergers with aLIGO ANITA 2018 workshop, ICRAR Curtin University, Perth, Australia, Feb 2018.

Department seminars

The dynamic magnetosphere of Swift J1818.0—1607
 Invited journal club talk, Max-Planck-Institut für Radioastronomie, Bonn, Germany, Dec 2020.

- **3.** Introduction to Bayesian parameter estimation with Bilby Astrophysics Coding Workshop, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, Aug 2020.
- Exploring the spectropolarimetric properties of radio-loud magnetars
 Mid-candidature colloquium, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, Aug 2020.
- Application of astrophysical inference to next generation pulsar data sets
 Confirmation of candidature colloquium, Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne, Australia, Sept 2019.

Posters

- **2.** Characterising rotational irregularities in the radio pulsar population with UTMOST. OzGrav Annual Retreat, Lorne, Australia, Nov 2019.
- 1. Measuring eccentricity in binary black hole inspirals with gravitational waves.
 Astronomical Society of Australia Annual Science Meeting, Melbourne, Australia, Jul 2018.